Guide to the Congregational Church Records
Yale University Divinity School Library
Congregational Church Records
1709-1983
RG 56
Yale University Divinity School Library
22.5
(67 boxes)
The Congregational Church Records of Record Group 56 are an open collection of primarily printed material dating from approximately 1795-1983. Records of various official bodies are encompassed by the record group as it documents churches of Congregational polity individually and in cooperation on local, state, national and international levels.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers.
Biographical / Historical
Congregationalism is defined as the form of church polity which rests on the independence and autonomy of each local church. This local autonomy has not prevented churches from forming county, state and national associations for mutual support and cooperative service. Historically, for Congregationalists, the term 'church' has been seen as applicable only to the local congregation and the wider associations have not had binding authority in matters related to doctrine and church discipline.
Over the years, Congregational churches in both Great Britain and the United States have followed a path toward union with like-minded bodies. In 1832, the county associations of Great Britain combined to form the Congregational Union of England and Wales. This Union merged with the Presbyterian Church of England in 1972 to form the United Reformed Church. In the United States, the National Council of the Congregational Churches and the General Convention of the Christian Churches formed a union in 1931, becoming The General Council of Congregational and Christian Churches. Under this union, local churches were free to continue as Congregational or as Christian Churches. A merger between the Congregational and Christian Churches and the Evangelical and Reformed Church was begun in 1957 and completed in July of 1961, resulting in the formation of the United Church of Christ. This merger was the cause of considerable controversy, being opposed by those who feared it would cause a lessening of traditional Congregational autonomy.
Scope and Contents
I. International Records
II. Congregational Churches in the U.S.: Publications Related to Doctrine, Polity and History
III. Congregational Churches in the U.S.: National Organizations and Meetings
IV. Congregational Churches in the U.S.: National Meetings
V. Congregational Churches in the U.S.: State and Local Records
Records of various official bodies are encompassed by the record group as it documents churches of Congregational polity individually and in cooperation on local, state, national and international levels.
The researcher should be aware that additional records similar to those appearing in this record group may appear in the Library's cataloged collections.
The majority of the records document Congregationalism in the United States (Series II through V), including material from most of the 50 states. While some of the publications may be of marginal interest, other portions of the material provide rich resources for historical research. The records of the Annual Meetings of the General Associations or Conferences of Connecticut, Illinois, Maine, Massachusetts, Nebraska, New Hampshire, New York, Ohio, Rhode Island and Vermont are relatively complete. Local associations within Connecticut and Massachusetts are also well represented.
The publications in Series II date from 1811 to 1969 and are primarily organized by format. Of particular interest in Series II is the pamphlet and ephemeral material published from 1939 to 1961 which documents the controversy surrounding the merger of the Congregational and Christian Churches and the Evangelical and Reformed Church. Similar material is available in the papers of Henry David Gray, Manuscript Group No. 52.
The National Organizations of Series III are primarily those related to educational, church building, church unity and ministerial support. These organizations are listed alphabetically. There are few records of national organizations devoted to home or foreign mission activity in this record group. Such documents are located elsewhere in the Library's collection.
The State and Local Records of Series V are primarily organized alphabetically by state and within each state according to the following categories:
A. Statewide organizations and meetings
B. Intrastate organizations and meetings
C. Individual church records
The records in Category A include the minutes, reports, proceedings and other publications of organizations and meetings which had delegates from throughout a state. The minutes and reports of annual meetings appear first in Category A, organized in chronological order under the official name of the gathering, the designation of which varied over time and from state to state. In some states, the pamphlet containing the minutes of the annual association, conference or convention meeting also included the annual report of the state missionary society.
The organizations and meetings represented in Category B of Series V are those with membership drawn from an area within a state, usually a county or municipality. The records of these groups are listed alphabetically by the name of the organization or gathering.
Records of individual churches are included in Series V only for states other than the New England states. Records of individual Congregational churches in the six New England states are located in Record Group 48, New England Church Records.
A fourth category, Regional organizations and meetings, includes organizations with membership drawn from more than one state or portions of more than one state.
Arrangement
I. International Records
II. Congregational Churches in the U.S.: Publications Related to Doctrine, Polity and History
III. Congregational Churches in the U.S.: National Organizations and Meetings
IV. Congregational Churches in the U.S.: National Meetings
V. Congregational Churches in the U.S.: State and Local Records
Congregational churches -- United States; Evangelical and Reformed Church; General Council of the Congregational and Christian Churches of the United States; United Church of Christ
- International Records, Series I
  - International Congregational Councils
    - First Annual, London, 1891 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Second Annual, Boston, 1899 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Third Annual, Edinburgh, 1908 (Box 65, Folder 273)
    - Sixth Annual, Wellesley, 1949 (Box 65, Folder 273)
    - Seventh Annual, St. Andrews, Scotland, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Congregational News Service, 1956-1957 (Box 67, Folder 14)
  - Congregational Churches in Australia
    - Report, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Congregational Churches in Canada
    - Report, 1853 (Box 1, Folder 4A)
  - Congregational Churches in England and Wales
    - Report, 1829, 1831, 1833, 1834, 1839 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Report, 1840-1842, 1856, 1862 (Box 1, Folder 5A)
    - Report, 1865, 1873 (Box 1, Folder 5B)
    - Report, 1884, 1886, 1889 (Box 1, Folder 5C)
    - Report, 1893, 1898, 1924, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Congregational Union of England and Wales Oversight and Covenant, 1960 (Box 67, Folder 26)
    - Congregational Central Youth Council, ca. 1954 (Box 67, Folder 26)
  - Congregational Churches in Scotland
    - Report, 1846, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Union Jubilee Number of The Scottish Congregationalist, 1946 (Box 67, Folder 13)
  - Congregational Federation
    - Report, 1980, 1982 (Box 66, Folder 279)
    - Congregational Quarterly, 1983-1984 (Box 67, Folder 25)
  - Congregational Union of New South Wales
    - Report, 1963 (Box 66, Folder 280)
- Congregational Churches in the United States: Pamphlets Related to Doctrine, Polity, and History, Series II
  - Handbooks, Platforms, Creeds
    - Miscellaneous, 1811, 1837, 1846-1894, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Miscellaneous, 1905, 1908, 1915, 1922-1940, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Miscellaneous, 1820, 1823, 1829, 1830 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Miscellaneous, 1871-1925 (Box 2, Folder 9A)
    - Miscellaneous, 1938-1955 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Miscellaneous, 1971, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Reports
    - Miscellaneous, 1852, 1855, 1856-1959, 1865-1938, 1948, 1969, n.d. (Box 2A, Folder 12)
  - Re. Worship
    - Selections from The Pilgrim Hymnal; The Council Hymnal, 1910, n.d. (Box 67, Folder 16)
    - Services of the Church Nos. 2,3,5-8 (United Church of Christ), 1969 (Box 67, Folder 17)
  - Material Related to the Merger of the Congregational Christian Churches and the Evangelical and Reformed Church
    - Anti-Merger Material
      - Miscellaneous, 1939-1946 (Box 2A, Folder 13)
      - Miscellaneous, 1947-1948 (Box 2A, Folder 14)
      - Miscellaneous, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 15)
      - Miscellaneous, 1950-1951 (Box 3, Folder 16)
      - Miscellaneous, 1952-1954 (Box 3, Folder 17)
      - Miscellaneous, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 18)
      - Miscellaneous, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Pro-Merger Material
      - Miscellaneous, 1942-1946 (Box 3, Folder 20)
      - Miscellaneous, 1947 (Box 3, Folder 21)
      - Miscellaneous, 1948 (Box 3, Folder 22)
      - Miscellaneous, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 23)
      - Miscellaneous, 1950-1961 (Box 3, Folder 24)
      - Miscellaneous, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 25)
      - Miscellaneous, 1953 (Box 67, Folder 6)
      - Broadside depicting history of merging bodies to form United Church of Christ; brochures about United Church of Christ, 1966, n.d. (Box 67, Folder 15)
- Congregational Churches in the United States: National Organizations and Institutions, 1873, 1903; Series III
  - American Congregational Association, 1873, 1903 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - American Congregational Union, 1878, 1882, 1899, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Board of Committee of Ministerial Relief (Including Annuity Fund and Pilgrim Memorial Fund), 1890-1937 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Board of Pastoral Supply, 1907-1910 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Commission on Comity, Federation and Unity (Box 65, Folder 274)
  - Committee Appointed to Prepare a Manual of Congregationalism, 1895 (Box 65, Folder 275)
  - Committee on Church Unity, 1913 (Box 65, Folder 274)
  - Committee on Minsterial Responsibility, ca. 1877 (Box 65, Folder 275)
  - Committee on Union with Free Baptists and other Denominations, ca. 1894 (Box 65, Folder 274)
  - Congregational Board of Publication, 1854, 1859 (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Congregational Board of Publication, 1860 (Box 67, Folder 7)
  - Congregational Church Building Society, 1903, 1923 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Congregational Church Building Society, 1910 (Box 67, Folder 8)
  - Congregational Education Society, 1931-1935 (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Congregational Foundation for Education, 1924, 1925 (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Congregational Home Missionary Society, 1895, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 33A)
  - Congregational Sunday School Extension Society, 1924 (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Congregational Sunday-School and Publishing Society, 1894 (Box 67, Folder 23)
  - Congregational Training School for Women, Chicago, 1912, 1917 (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Council for Social Action (see also RG: 49), 1952, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Laymen's Fellowship, 1941 (Box 4, Folder 36A)
  - Missions Council of Congregational Christian Churches, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 36B)
  - National Council Committee on Industry, 1910 (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - National Council Laymen's Advisory Committee, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 37A)
  - National Council Publications on: Polity, Doctrine, History of the Congregational Churches; the National Council, Membership, etc., 1865, 1880, 1886 (Box 4, Folder 37B)
  - National Federation of Churches and Christian Workers (Box 4, Folder 37C)
  - National Service Commission, 1918 (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Pension Boards (Booklets includes: The Annuity Fund for Congregational Ministers; Retired Fund for Lay Workers; Ministerial Relief Division of the Board of the Home Missions), 1946 (Box 4, Folder 37E)
- Congregational Churches in the United States: National Meetings, Series IV
  - National Council or Conventional Meetings
    - Miscellaneous, 1852-1858 (Box 5, Folder 38)
    - Miscellaneous, 1865, 1871, 1892 (Box 5, Folder 39)
    - Miscellaneous, 1915 (Box 5, Folder 40)
    - Miscellaneous, 1915 (Box 5, Folder v.1)
    - Miscellaneous, 1923-1929 (Box 5, Folder 41)
  - General Council of the Congregational Christian Churches
    - Advance Reports, programs, 1942-1961 (Box 66, Folder 278)
  - Other Meetings
    - Anniversary of the Congregational Societies, 1882 (Box 5, Folder 42)
    - Congregational Christian Midwinter Meetings, 1940, 1942 (Box 66, Folder 277)
- Congregational Churches in the United States: Regional, State, and Local Records, Series V
  - Alabama
    - Statewide organizations and meetings
      - Minutes of State Convention, 1905, 1907 (Box 6, Folder 43)
  - Alaska (see regional organizations)
  - California (see also regional organizations)
    - Statewide organizations and meetings
      - Minutes of General Association, 1857, 1863, 1867, 1874, 1882, 1888, 1889 (Box 6, Folder 44)
    - Intrastate organizations and meetings
      - Southern California Conference, 1895, 1899, 1917, 1920, 1922 (Box 6, Folder 45)
      - Northern California Conference, 1911 (Box 6, Folder 45A)
      - Los Angeles Association, 1938 (Box 64, Folder 233)
      - Bay Association, 1930 (Box 64, Folder 233)
    - Individual Churches
      - Berkeley: First Congregational Church, 1948 (Box 6, Folder 46)
      - Pokegama Congregational Church, n.d. (Box 67, Folder 21)
      - Los Angeles: First Congregational Church, 1901, 1959, 1964, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 46)
      - San Diego: Chinese Community Church, 1947 (Box 6, Folder 46)
      - San Francisco: First Congregational Church, 1898- 1915 (Box 6, Folder 47)
      - South Pasadena: Oneonta Congregational Church, 1924, 1926 (Box 6, Folder 47)
  - Colorado
    - Statewide Organizations and Meetings
      - Minutes of Congregational Association, 1893, 1911 (Box 6, Folder 48)
      - Colorado Congregational Conference, n.d. (Box 64, Folder 237)
    - Individual Churches
      - Boulder: First Congregational Church, 1939 (Box 6, Folder 48)
      - Colorado Springs: First Congregational Church, 1898 (Box 67, Folder 22)
  - Connecticut
    - Statewide organizations and meetings
      - Minutes of General Association, 1809, 1812, 1825-1830 (Box 7, Folder 49)
      - Minutes of General Association, 1829-1843 (Box 63, Folder v.1)
      - Minutes of General Association, 1831-1837 (Box 7, Folder 50)
      - Minutes of General Association, 1838-1843 (Box 7, Folder 51)
      - Minutes of General Association, 1844-1850 (Box 53, Folder v.1A)
      - Minutes of General Association, 1851-1860 (Box 53, Folder v.2)
      - Minutes of General Association, 1861-1865 (Box 53, Folder v.3)
      - Minutes of General Association, 1887-1899, n.d. (Box 53, Folder 51B)
      - Minutes of General Association, General Conference, Connecticut Conference of Congregational Christian Churches, 1866-1870 (Box 53, Folder v.4)
      - MGA, GC, CCCCC, 1870-1875 (Box 54, Folder v.5)
      - MGA, GC, CCCCC, 1875-1880 (Box 54, Folder v.6)
      - MGA, GC, CCCCC, 1880-1885 (Box 54, Folder v.7)
      - MGA, GC, CCCCC, 1886-1890 (Box 54, Folder v.8)
      - MGA, GC, CCCCC, 1891-1895 (Box 55, Folder v.9)
      - MGA, GC, CCCCC, 1896-1900 (Box 55, Folder v.10)
      - MGA, GC, CCCCC, 1901-1905 (Box 55, Folder v.11)
      - MGA, GC, CCCCC, 1906-1910 (Box 55, Folder v.12)
      - MGA, GC, CCCCC, 1911-1920 (Box 56, Folder v.13)
      - MGA, GC, CCCCC, 1921-1926 (Box 56, Folder v.14)
      - MGA, GC, CCCCC, 1927-1932 (Box 56, Folder v.15)
      - MGA, GC, CCCCC, 1933-1938 (Box 56, Folder v.16)
      - MGA, GC, CCCCC, 1939-1942 (Box 7, Folder 52)
      - MGA, GC, CCCCC, 1943, 1944, 1946, 1949-1952 (Box 8, Folder 53)
      - MGA, GC, CCCCC, 1953-1958, 1960, 1961, 1962 (Box 9, Folder 54)
      - MGA, GC, CCCCC, 1871-1880 (Box 56, Folder 51C)
      - General Association circular letters, appeals for Fund for Ministers, 1864, 1874-1887 (Box 64, Folder 215)
      - General Conference programmes, reports, papers, 1836-1862, 1868-1884 (Box 10, Folder 56)
      - GC programmes, reports, papers, 1885-1940, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 57)
      - General Association programmes, 1878-1898 (Box 10, Folder 57A)
      - Connecticut Congregational Club, 1877-1890, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 58)
      - Connecticut Congregational Calendar, 1886-1887 (Box 10, Folder 58)
      - Council of Congregational Women of Connecticut, 1936 (Box 10, Folder 59)
      - Ecclesiastical Council convened at Plymouth, 1856 (Box 10, Folder 59)
      - Connecticut Home Evangelization Report, 1860-1861 (Box 10, Folder 59)
      - Convention of the Consociations of Connecticut, 1854 (Box 11, Folder 73)
      - Minutes of Annual Meetings of the Congregational Churches of Connecticut, 1881 (Box 11, Folder 73)
      - Digest and Rules and Usages in the Consociations and Associations of Connecticut, 1862 (Box 64, Folder 217)
      - Connecticut Fellowship of Congregational Christian Churches, 1962-1978 (Box 64, Folder 223)
      - Connecticut Fund for Ministers, 1895-1902 (Box 64, Folder 236)
    - Intrastate organizations and meetings
      - Fairfield Country: General, 1886, 1939, 1952 (Box 10A, Folder 60)
      - FC: East Association and Consociation, 1832-1860, 1863-1872 (Box 10A, Folder 61)
      - FC: West Association and Consociation, 1824-1852, 1859-1896 (Box 10A, Folder 62)
      - FC: Clerical Association, 1925 (Box 10A, Folder 62)
      - Farmington Valley Association, n.d. (Box 64, Folder 220)
      - Hartford County: North Consociation, 1846 (Box 10A, Folder 63)
      - HC: South Consociation/ Conference, 1866, 1867, 1881 (Box 10A, Folder 63)
      - Litchfield County: General, 1852 (Box 10A, Folder 64)
      - LC: East Association and Consociation, 1847 (Box 10A, Folder 65)
      - LC: North Association and Consociation, 1851-1853, 1863-1869 (Box 10A, Folder 66)
      - LC: Northwest Conference, 1886-1912 (Box 11, Folder 67)
      - LC: NC: Annual Survey, 1909-1925 (Box 64, Folder 224)
      - LC: NC: AS, 1913-1930 (Box 11, Folder 68)
      - LC: South Consociation, ca. 1841 (Box 67, Folder 10)
      - LC: South Consociation, 1842, 1850, 1855 (Box 11, Folder 69)
      - LC: Northeast Association, n.d. (Box 64, Folder 219)
      - Middlesex County, 1860-1866, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 70)
      - Naugatuck Valley Association, 1934 (Box 64, Folder 218)
      - New Haven County: East Consociation, 1709-1927, 1854, 1893, 1925 (Box 11, Folder 71)
      - New Haven County: East Consociation, 1854, n.d. (Box 67, Folder 1)
      - NHC: West Association and Consociation; Conference, 1836-1909, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 72)
      - NHC: West Consociation, 1862 (Box 67, Folder 11)
      - NHC: New Haven Association, 1901 (Box 67, Folder 9)
      - NHC: New Haven Association, 1941 (Box 64, Folder 222)
      - Tolland County, 1888, 1943 (Box 64, Folder 216)
      - Windham Association, 1945 (Box 64, Folder 221)
      - New Haven Congregational Club, 1885-1914 (Box 11, Folder 73)
      - The Associated Pastors of New Haven Center, 1873 (Box 11, Folder 73)
      - The Congregational Union of New Haven, 1892 (Box 11, Folder 73)
      - New Haven Congregational Churches: City Missionary, 1861 (Box 11, Folder 73)
    - Individual Churches (See: Record Group 48)
  - District of Columbia
    - Individual Churches
      - First Congregational Church, 1868, 1869 (Box 11, Folder 73A)
      - Tabernacle Congregational Church, 1893 (Box 11, Folder 73A)
      - Mount Pleasant Congregational Christian Conference, 1911 (Box 11, Folder 73A)
  - Florida
    - Statewide organizations and meetings
      - Congregational Ecclesiastical Council, Tampa, 1901-1903 (Box 11, Folder 74)
      - General Congregational Association of Florida, 1902 (Box 11, Folder 74)
      - Florida Congregational Christian Conference, 1945, 1946 (Box 64, Folder 239)
  - Hawaii
    - Statewide Organizations and Meetings
      - Hawaii Conference of the United Church of Christ, 1963, 1964 (Box 64, Folder 240)
      - Hawaiian Evangelical Association, 1943-1951 (Box 64, Folder 241)
    - Individual Churches
      - Honolulu: Central Union Church, 1910 (Box 12, Folder 75)
      - H:CUC, 1911 (Box 12, Folder 76)
      - H:CUC, 1912 (Box 12, Folder 77)
      - H:CUC, 1913 (Box 12, Folder 78)
      - H: Fort St. Church, 1857 (Box 12, Folder 79)
      - H: Church of the Crossroads, 1954 (Box 12, Folder 79)
      - Kailua: Mokuaikaua Church, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 79)
  - Idaho (see also regional organizations)
    - Statewide organizations and meetings
      - Idaho Conference of Congregational Churches and Ministers (Box 65, Folder 242)
  - Illinois
    - Statewide organizations and meetings
      - Minutes of General Association, 1853-1854, 1856, 1858-1871 (Box 13, Folder 80)
      - Minutes of General Association, 1891-1892, 1894-1909 (Box 13, Folder 81)
      - Minutes of Congregational Conference, 1910-1926 (Box 14, Folder 82)
      - Reports of Officers and Committees - General Conference, 1925, 1926 (Box 14, Folder 83)
      - Historical Papers - General Association, 1869, 1894 (Box 14, Folder 84)
      - Memorial of the Congregational Ministers and Churches of the Illinois Association, 1863 (Box 67, Folder 12)
      - Illinois Society of Church History, Congregational, 1895 (Box 14, Folder 85)
      - Minutes of the Presbyterian and Congregational Convention, 1847 (Box 14, Folder 85)
      - Congregational and Christian Conference of Illinois, 1947 (Box 65, Folder 243)
      - Ex Parte Council of Congregational Churches, Wheaton, 1878 (Box 65, Folder 245)
    - Intrastate organizations and meetings
      - Chicago Congregational Club, 1883 (Box 14, Folder 86)
      - Chicago Congregational Association, 1941 (Box 65, Folder 244)
      - Chicago Congregational Union, n.d. (Box 65, Folder 244)
    - Individual Churches
      - Chicago: First Congregational Church, 1878 (Box 14, Folder 87)
      - Chicago: South Congregational Church, 1911 (Box 14, Folder 87)
      - Evanston: Asbury Avenue Congregational Church of Christ, 1900 (Box 14, Folder 88)
      - Evanston: First Congregational Church, 1927 (Box 14, Folder 88)
      - Galesburg: First Church of Christ, 1887 (Box 14, Folder 88)
      - Galesburg: Central Congregational Church, ca. 1860 (Box 14, Folder 88)
      - Galesburgh: Central Congregational Church, 1895 (Box 67, Folder 2)
      - Jacksonville: The Congregational Church, 1883, 1983 (Box 14, Folder 88A)
      - Morgan Co: Joy Prairie Congregational Church, 1895 (Box 14, Folder 88A)
      - Oak Park: First Congregational Church, 1913 (Box 14, Folder 88A)
      - Peoria: First Congregational Church, 1884 (Box 14, Folder 89)
      - Springfield: First Congregational Church, 1887 (Box 14, Folder 89)
  - Indiana
    - Statewide Organizations and Meetings
      - Indiana Congregational Christian Conference, 1935, 1943 (Box 14, Folder 89A)
      - General Association of the Congregational Churches and Ministers of Indiana, 1865, 1867, 1872 (Box 65, Folder 246)
    - Intrastate organizations and meetings
      - Central Association, n.d. (Box 65, Folder 247)
      - Central Association - handbill for annual meeting, 1880 (Box 67, Folder 19)
  - Iowa
    - Statewide organizations and meetings
      - General Association, 1840-1869, 1871-1880 (Box 15, Folder 90)
      - GA, 1881-1900 (Box 15, Folder 91)
      - GA, 1901-1910 (Box 16, Folder 92)
      - Congregational Conference, 1911, 1912 (Box 16, Folder 93)
      - CongregationalChristian Conference, n.d. (Box 65, Folder 248)
      - Manual issued by General Association, ca. 1870 (Box 16, Folder 94)
    - Intrastate organizations and meetings
      - Davenport Association, 1946 (Box 65, Folder 249)
      - Denmark Congregational Association, 1873 (Box 65, Folder 249)
      - Des Moines Association, n.d. (Box 65, Folder 249)